Oracle Labs, Switzerland Täfernstrasse 4 5405 Baden-Dättwil Switzerland

Phone: +41 78 9489 347 Address: Feldblumenstrasse 100, 8134 Adliswil E-mail: aleksandar.prokopec@gmail.com Website: http://axel22.github.io

### ALEKSANDAR PROKOPEC

Personal Information

Birth date: 6. August 1985.

Slovenian, married

Swiss Permit B (2014 – 2019)

Summary

I am a computer science researcher with 7 years of academic and industrial experience. I published 12 peer-reviewed research publications, and led multiple software projects, supervised EPFL-hosted open source projects with external funding from Google, and organized a highly successful Coursera massive open online course on reactive programming. In 2016, I created the Parallel Programming course at Coursera, where I was the main lecturer. The Parallel Programming course was one of the three parts of Coursera's Scala specialization program for the Scala programming language, which in total earned more than one million dollars. I have participated in several international collaborations with top universities and industrial partners. I participated on industrial and research conferences and meetups, held 9 invited talks, and authored a textbook on concurrent programming in Scala. Between 2014 and 2016, I worked at Google on systems for Big Data analytics. Since 2016, I work at Oracle Labs on Graal language infrastructure project.

Education

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Lausanne, Switzerland

2009 - 2014

Ph.D. in Computer Science Advisor: Martin Odersky

Committee: Douglas Lea, Erik Meijer, Viktor Kuncak, Ola Svensson

Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing, Zagreb, Croatia

2004 - 2009

M.A. in Computer Science Advisor: Marin Golub

Professional Experience

Principal Researcher, Oracle Labs, Zürich, Switzerland

2016 -

• Working on the Graal language infrastructure project, the next generation runtime for modern programming languages.

Software Engineer, Google Inc., Zürich, Switzerland Product area: Geo

2014 - 2016

- Maintaining a distributed logging infrastructure for Google Maps products.
- Working on a massively distributed system used to analyze Geo product usage.
- Led the implementation of a real-time distributed pipeline for spam detection. Awarded a Google Spot Bonus for this effort.
- Designed and implemented a test automation suite for product documentation.

Main organizer of the team-internal monthly Hackathon events.
 Awarded a Google Peer Bonus for this effort.

Scala Open Source Developer, Scala Team, Lausanne, Switzerland

- 2009 2016
- Designed and implemented Scala Coroutines language extension for first-class coroutines, used to facilitate asynchronous programming.
- Designed and implemented Parallel Collections support for data-parallel programming (part of the Scala programming language since 2011).
- Core part of the Futures and Promises working group, aimed to design the support for asynchronous programming (part of Scala programming language since 2012).
- Maintained and improved the Scala compiler and the Scala standard library.
- Engaged in various open-source activities: ScalaDays conference organization, Scala Workshop program committee member, Scala Improvement Proposal process, online education (MOOCs) and documentation, etc.

#### Collaborations

FORTH Institute of Computer Science (Greece),

2015 - now

Computer Architecture and VLSI Systems Laboratory

Research collaboration aimed at developing a novel high-performance concurrent data structures for traditional embedded systems.

Typesafe (USA), 2011 – now

Collaborating on maintenance, development, technology and innovation exchange related to the Scala project (~30 Scala developers).

Akka team (Sweden), 2011 – 2012

Member of the working group (~10 people) that developed a unifying asynchronous programming framework for Scala.

Stanford University (USA), 2011 – 2013

Pervasive Parallelism Laboratory

Collaborated on the LMS and Delite compiler frameworks and runtimes for parallel embedded domain-specific languages (~10 people). Designed high-performance data structures and collections frontends.

# Teaching Experience

Lecturer, Organizer, Parallel Programming Coursera MOOC on Parallel Programming.

2016

2015

External Lecturer, Co-Organizer, Reactive Programming and Parallelism Co-organized, prepared materials and exercises, led teaching staff (~7 people) on the undergraduate course on parallel, distributed, and asynchronous programming at EPFL, ~90 students.

Lead Organizer, Principles of Reactive Programming Coursera MOOC on reactive programming in Scala, with 2 iterations and >60,000 participants so far.

2013

• Coordinated a team of three lecturers during recording and lecture material production.

2

- Led graduate student teaching staff (~8 people), directed content production, designed and implemented exercise materials, managed the production of lecture videos, organized community TAs on Coursera.
- Received the EPFL IC Teaching Award for this effort.

Teaching Assistant, Functional Programming in Scala Required EPFL undergraduate course on functional programming (~160 students).

2010-2013

#### Research Interests

My focus is design and implementation of frameworks, programming languages, and runtime support for concurrent, parallel and distributed software development. I proposed and implemented novel persistent, concurrent and incremental data structures that support these programming paradigms. I use the Scala programming language as both the underlying development platform and research vehicle.

Thesis

Data Structures and Algorithms for Data-Parallel Computing EPFL 2014 in a Managed Runtime

Books

Learning Concurrent Programming in Scala Packt Publishing 2014
Aleksandar Prokopec

**Publications** 

Authored 13 international research publications and several technical reports.

Pluggable Scheduling for the Reactor Programming Model AGERE 2016 Aleksandar Prokopec

AGERE 2016, co-located with SPLASH

Isolates, Channels and Event Streams for Composable

Onward! 2015

Distributed Programming

Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky

Onward! 2015

Aleksandar Prokopec

Conc-Trees for Functional and Parallel Programming

Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky

Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2015

3

LCPC 2015

SnapQueue: Lock-Free Queue with Constant Time Snapshots

SCALA 2015

Aleksandar Prokopec

Scala Symposium 2015, co-located with PLDI

Efficient Lock-Free Work-stealing Iterators for Data-Parallel Collections

PDP 2015

Aleksandar Prokopec, Dmitry Petrashko, Martin Odersky

Parallel, Distributed and Network-Based Processing 2015

Containers and Aggregates, Mutators and Isolates

SCALA 2014

for Reactive Programming

Aleksandar Prokopec, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky Annual Scala Workshop 2014, co-located with ECOOP

Near Optimal Work-Stealing Tree Scheduler for Highly Irregular Data-Parallel Workloads LCPC 2013

Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky

Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2013

Composition and Reuse with Compiled Domain-Specific Languages

ECOOP 2013

Arvind K. Sujeeth, Tiark Rompf, Kevin J. Brown,

HyoukJoong Lee, Hassan Chafi, Victoria Popic, Michael Wu,

Aleksandar Prokopec, Vojin Jovanovic, Martin Odersky, Kunle Olukotun

European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming 2013

FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent

LCPC 2012

**Dataflow Abstraction** 

Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Tobias Schlatter

Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky

Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2012

Concurrent Tries with Efficient Non-blocking Snapshots

PPOPP 2012

Aleksandar Prokopec, Nathan Bronson, Phil Bagwell, Martin Odersky Symposium on Principles and Practice of Parallel Programming 2012

Lock-Free Resizeable Concurrent Tries

LCPC 2011

Aleksandar Prokopec, Phil Bagwell, Martin Odersky

Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing 2011

A Generic Parallel Collection Framework

Euro-Par 2011

Aleksandar Prokopec, Phil Bagwell, Tiark Rompf, Martin Odersky

Euro-Par 2011

Adaptive Mutation Operator Cycling

ICADIWT 2009

Aleksandar Prokopec, Marin Golub International Conference on the Applications

of Digital Information and Web Technologies 2009

Achieving Efficient Work-Stealing for Data-Parallel Collections Aleksandar Prokopec, Martin Odersky	April 2013
Multi-Lane FlowPools: A Detailed Look Tobias Schlatter, Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky	September 2012
FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent Dataflow Abstraction – Proofs Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Philipp Haller	June 2012
Cache-Aware Lock-Free Concurrent Hash Tries Aleksandar Prokopec, Phil Bagwell, Martin Odersky	June 2011
<ul> <li>Scala Programming Language, Scala team member</li> <li>Scala Coroutines, lead         Scala language extension for first-class coroutines,         used for easier asynchronous programming.</li> <li>Reactors Framework for Distributed Programming, lead         Programming framework aimed at building asynchronous,         composable, distributed systems.</li> <li>Scala-Blitz – High-Performance Data-Parallelism Framework, lead         Scala module for highly efficient data-parallel programming.</li> <li>ScalaMeter Benchmarking Framework, lead         Microbenchmarking and performance regression testing framewor         for Scala and JVM, adopted in various open source projects.</li> <li>Scala Futures &amp; Promises (Scala Improvement Proposal 14), team         Asynchronous programming framework for Scala, used as a         basic building block for other concurrency frameworks within         the Scala ecosystem (part of standard Scala distribution since 2012</li> <li>Parallel Collections Framework, lead         Scala standard library module for data-parallel programming         (part of the standard Scala distribution in 2011).</li> </ul>	rk member
<ul> <li>Java Group at Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing, Zagreb,</li> <li>VHDLLab, team member         Award-winning online educational VHDL editor for modeling and simulation of digital circuits (used as part of the computer science curriculum at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing in Zagreb since 2007).     </li> </ul>	
Google Spot Bonus for the Distributed Real-Time Spam Detection Proje Google Peer Bonus for the Team Hackathon Initiative Nominated for the Patrick Denantes Doctoral Thesis Award EPFL Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award LCPC Best Paper Presentation Award	ct 2015 2015 2014 2013 2011

Open Source

Honors and Awards

EPFL Computer Science Fellowship University of Zagreb Rector Award for Best Project (VHDLLab) Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing Josip Loncar Award Faculty of Electrical Engineering and Computing Josip Loncar Award Participation in the International Physics Olympiad (IPhO) 1st Place in the Croatian National Physics Competition (Finals) Participation in the Croatian National Physics Competition (Finals) Participation in the Croatian National Physics Competition (Finals)	2009 - 2010 2008 2007 2006 2004 2004 2002 2001
Gave over 20 academic and industrial talks, 8 as an invited speaker.	
First-Class Coroutines for the Scala Programming Language Developer Conference Talk Lake District, UK, September 12, 2016	Scala World 2016
Reactors - Road to Composable Distributed Computing Developer Conference Talk Berlin, Germany, June, 2016	ScalaDays 2016
Reactor Model for Composable Distributed Computing Developer Conference Talk Zurich, Switzerland, March 3, 2016	Days Zurich 2016
Isolates, Channels and Event Streams for Composable Distributed Programming Academic Conference Talk Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA, October 29, 2015	Onward! 2015
Scala – The Learning Curve Developer Conference Talk Zurich, Switzerland, October 23, 2015	Jazoon 2015
Conc-Tree Data Structure for Functional and Parallel Programming Academic Conference Talk Raleigh, North Carolina, USA, September 10, 2015	LCPC 2015
SnapQueue: Lock-Free Queue with Constant Time Snapshots Academic Conference Talk Portland, Oregon, USA, June 13, 2015	SCALA 2015
ScalaMeter – Performance Regression Testing Framework Academic Meetup Talk ETH, Zürich, Switzerland, September 11, 2014	VM Meetup 2014
Containers and Aggregates, Mutators and Isolates for Reactive Programming Academic Conference Talk Uppsala, Sweden, July 28, 2014	SCALA 2014
Reactive Collections and 3D Engine Design	ScalaDays 2014

Selected Talks

Industrial Conference Talk (800 attendees)

Berlin, Germany, June 24, 2014

Macro-based Scala Parallel Collections

Scala eXchange 2013

Industrial Conference Talk (350 attendees, invited talk)

London, UK, December 2, 2013

Work-Stealing Tree Scheduling

LCPC 2013

Academic Conference Talk

San Jose, CA, USA, September 26, 2013

Scala as a Research Tool

ECOOP 2013

ECOOP Tutorial (w/ Heather Miller and Philipp Haller)

Montpellier, France, July 1, 2013

Scala Performance Regression Testing

Scala eXchange 2012

Industrial Conference Talk (invited talk)

London, UK, November 19, 2012

Parallel Concurrent Hash Tries

ScalaDays 2012

Industrial Conference Talk (400 attendees)

London, UK, April 18, 2012

Concurrent Hash Tries in Scala

Croatian IEEE Chapter Meetup

Academic Meetup Talk (invited talk) Zagreb, Croatia, April 11, 2012

Concurrent Tries with Efficient Non-Blocking Snapshots

PPOPP 2012

Academic Conference Talk

New Orleans, Louisiana, USA, February 29, 2012

Lock-Free Resizeable Concurrent Tries

LCPC 2011

Academic Conference Talk

Fort Collins, CO, USA, September 9, 2011

Generic Parallel Collection Framework

Euro-Par 2011

Academic Conference Talk

Bordeaux, France, September 2, 2011

**Parallel Collections** 

Scala eXchange 2011

Industrial Conference Talk (280 attendees, invited talk)

London, UK, June 15, 2011

Scala Parallel Collections

ScalaDays 2011

Industrial Conference Talk

Palo Alto, CA, USA, June 3, 2011

Introduction to Scala

JUG Meetup 2011

Industrial Talk, Java User Group Grenoble (invited talk)

Grenoble, France, March, 2011

Parallel Collections	ScalaDays 2010
Industrial Conference Talk (150 attendees, invited talk)	•

Lausanne, Switzerland, April 15, 2010

## External Service

Reviewer or program committee member of 8 scientific conferences and journals.

Programming based on Actors, Agents, and Decentralized Control (AGERE! 20	o16), pro-
gram committee	2016
International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (ICPADS 2016),	, program
committee	2016
High-Level Parallel Programming and Applications (HLPP 2016), program c	ommittee
2016	
On Principles of Distributed Systems (OPODIS 2015), external reviewer	2015
Transactions on Computers 2015, journal submission reviewer	2015
Scala Workshop 2014, program committee	7/2014
High-Level Parallel Programming and Applications 2014, external reviewer	4/2014
ECOOP 2013, external reviewer	7/2013
Scala Workshop 2013, program committee (co-chair)	7/2013
ScalaDays 2010, external reviewer	6/2010
ICADIWT 2009, external reviewer	8/2009

## Supervised Projects<sup>1</sup>

Supervised 14 bachelor and master student projects.

Joël Rossier, MacroGL Scala.JS Backend B.Sc. level	2/2014 - 6/2014
Sven Reber, MacroGL API Extensions B.Sc. level	2/2014 – 6/2014
Gwangbae Choi, ScalaMeter Inline Benchmarking B.Sc. level	2/2014 – 6/2014
Kristof Szabo, ScalaMeter Java API B.Sc. level	2/2014 – 6/2014
Nicolas Stucki, Scala Multiset Collection M.Sc. level	9/2013 - 1/2014
Timo Babst, Data-Parallel Raytracer B.Sc. level	9/2013 - 1/2014
Clément Moutet, Data-Parallel Flocking Algorithm B.Sc. level	9/2013 - 1/2014
Roman Zoller, ScalaMeter D3js Frontend M.Sc. level	2/2013 - 6/2013
Tobias Schlatter, FlowSeqs: Barrier-Free ParSeqs M.Sc. level, co-supervision w/ Philipp Haller & Heather Miller	9/2012 - 1/2013

¹EPFL research labs prepare projects for B.Sc./M.Sc. students to complete for credits. These projects are designed and supervised by EPFL doctoral assistants.

Roger Vion, Improvements to ScalaMeter B.Sc. level	9/2012 - 1/2013
Tobias Schlatter, Multi-Lane FlowPools M.Sc. level, co-supervision w/ Philipp Haller & Heather Miller	2/2012 - 6/2012
Bruno Studer, A Non-Blocking Concurrent Queue Algorithm B.Sc. level	2/2012 - 6/2012
Ngoc Duy Pham, Scala Benchmarking Suite – Performance Regression Pinpointing M.Sc. level	8/2011 - 1/2012
Pamela Delgado, Scala Invariant Verifier M.Sc. level	8/2011 - 1/2012
Supervised 4 Google Summer of Code projects.	
Krzysztof Janosz, ScalaMeter –- Binary Compatible Serialization Format and Invocation Measurers	5/2015 - 9/2015
Dmitry Petrashko, Specializing Parallel Collections with Scala Macros	5/2013 - 9/2013
Ivan Oreskovic, Porting Scala Parallel Collections to the Android Platform	5/2012 - 9/2012
Heather Miller, Parallel Collections Extensions	5/2011 - 0/2011

GSoC Projects<sup>2</sup>

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup>The Scala Team is a regular host of Google Summer of Code Projects. These are 3-month paid projects offered to students all over the world, sponsored by Google and supervised by members of various open-source organizations.

#### References

Martin Odersky

Faculty of Computer, Communication, and Information Science

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne

**L** +41 21 693 68 63

⊠ martin.odersky@epfl.ch

Philipp Haller

School of Computer Science and Communication

KTH Royal Institute of Technology

**L** +41 76 205 39 32

⊠ phaller@kth.se